A Finding Aid to the Ivan C. Karp Personal Papers and OK Harris Works of Art gallery records, 1960-2014, in the Archives of American Art AAA.okharr
Archives of American Art
Ivan C. Karp personal papers and OK Harris Works of Art gallery records
1960-2014
AAA.okharr
Archives of American Art
80.3 Linear feet
The Ivan C. Karp papers and OK Harris Works of Art gallery records measure 80.3 linear feet and are dated 1960-2014. The collection documents the operation and activities of the contemporary art gallery founded by Ivan C. Karp in the SoHo area of Manhattan. Exhibition files, artists' files, printed material and photographic materials reveal the wide range of artists represented by OK Harris and the gallery's role in introducing Photo-realism to the public. Aso included are administrative files, prints by OK Harris artists, business and personal correspondence, 39 journals by Karp spanning a period of 62 years, and other personal papers. Material pre-dating the 1969 establishment of OK Harris Works of Art consists of printed items and a few letters.
Karp, Ivan C., 1926-
OK Harris Gallery.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged in 8 series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1960-2013 (Boxes 1-2B; 2.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Administrative Files, 1969-2014 (Box 3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1969-2014 (Boxes 3-4; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Artists' Files, 1967-2014 (Boxes 4-38, 80; 34 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1963-2014 (Boxes 38-44, 80, OV 88 - OV 90; 5.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, 1970s-circa 1980 (Box 44, OV 81-OV 87; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographic Materials, 1960s-2014, bulk 1969-1999 (Boxes 44-76; 32 linear feet)
Series 8: Ivan C. Karp papers, 1961-2012 (Boxes 75-79; 4 linear feet)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Marilynn Karp, wife of Ivan C. Karp, donated scattered papers in 2011 and 2013, and the bulk of the collection in 2014.
Scope and Contents note
The Ivan C. Karp papers and OK Harris Works of Art gallery records measure 80.3 linear feet and are dated 1960-2014. The collection documents the operation and activities of the contemporary art gallery founded by Ivan C. Karp in the SoHo area of Manhattan. Exhibition files, artists' files, printed material, and photographic materials reveal the wide range of artists represented by OK Harris and the gallery's role in introducing Photo-realism to the public. Also included are administrative files, prints by OK Harris artists, business and personal correspondence, 39 journals by Karp spanning a period of 62 years, and other personal papers. Material pre-dating the 1969 establishment of OK Harris Works of Art consists of printed items and a few letters.
Correspondence, both professional and personal, is with museums, galleries, art dealers, art collectors, and graduate students. Artists John Baeder, Deborah Butterfield, John Clem Clarke, John DeAndrea, Jim Dine, Leonard Dufresne, Robert Ginder, Ralph Goings, Duane Hanson, Richard McLean and Tom Wesselmann are among the correspondents.
Admininstrative files concern the daily operation of OK Harris Works of Art. Included are instructions regarding administrative functions and forms for routine activities to enable employees to conduct business in Ivan Karp's absence. Along with files about other items occasionally sold at the gallery, there are files about projects of interest to the Karps, sample announcements, invitations, and advertisements.
Exhibition files document group shows, collectibles and antique exhibitions, summer invitationals, and special event exhibitions at OK Harris Works of Art. The files include photographs and slides, schedules, lists of titles and prices, artists' resumes, installation layouts, reviews and publicity materials, and other items.
The largest series (34 linear feet), artists' files, documents the gallery's relationships with artists throughout its 45 year history. Files are comprised of biographical information, correspondence, notes, publicity and other printed material (including a few items pre-dating the gallery). Among the many transactions recorded are arrangements for and documentation of solo exhibitions at OK Harris. There are photographs, slides and color transparencies of individual works, and some views of exhibition installations. John Baeder, Muriel Castanis, Don Celender, Ralph Goings, John Kacere, Richard McLean, Robert Rohm and John Salt are among the most extensively documented artists.
Printed material produced by OK Harris Works of Art includes exhibition catalogs, exhibition announcements, invitations, checklists, price lists posters, and notices of gallery sponsored events and activities. Printed material from other sources consists of exhibition reviews, articles about Ivan and Marilynn Karp, OK Harris Works of Art, and the gallery's artists. These appeared in art and mainstream periodicals, newspapers, exhibition catalogs, and books. Also found are posters, reproductions of artwork, and miscellaneous printed items. Artwork consists of 40 prints by artists affiliated with OK Harris. Most are signed; 2 are black and white prints, the remainder are color lithographs. Included is Radical Realism I, a set of 6 prints issued by Mother Lode Editions, 1972.
Thirty-two linear feet of photographs, negatives, slides, transparencies and digital images are of artwork by OK Harris artists, exhibition installation views, and miscellaneous subjects. Photographs of artwork by 59 OK Harris artists are found in binders called "Artists' Photo Books." Installation views of exhibitions held at OK Harris Works of Art during its 45 year history fill 61 binders. Miscellaneous subjects include OK Harris office space, galleries and staff. Also found are photographs of group shows, art fairs, and gallery artists' exhibitions at other venues.
The Ivan C. Karp personal papers include obituaries from print and internet sources along with other biographical information, published versions of brief interviews conducted for various purposes, writings, a few materials relating to business and academic activities, and some personal photographs. Journals, 1950-2012 (bulk 1991-2012) record travel, daily activities, and reflections.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art are oral history interviews with Ivan C. Karp conducted by Richard Brown Baker, 1963 October 18; by Paul Cummings, 1969 March 12; and by Ronny Cohen, 1986 April 17-1988 October 18. The Marilynn Gelfman Karp Collection of Ephemera owned by the New-York Historical Society includes OK Harris printed material, prints, and posters.
Historical note
OK Harris Works of Art specialized in a wide range of contemporary art and was known for its early support of Photo-realism. When it opened in 1969, the gallery was one of the first to operate in the SoHo area of Manhattan and its presence helped shape the neighborhood's development into a vibrant arts district.
Ivan C. Karp (1926-2012), the founder of OK Harris Works of Art, established a reputation in the art world while co-director of Leo Castelli Gallery from 1959-1969. He is credited with launching the careers of Pop artists such as Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Robert Rauschenberg, John Chamberlain, Tom Wesselmann, and Claes Oldenburg. Karp wrote, published, and lectured extensively on art and the art business. He was the author of a romantic novel about New York life, Doobie Doo (published in 1965, front cover by Roy Lichtenstein, back cover by Andy Warhol) and his short stories were published in literary reviews. Karp was actively involved in architectural preservation efforts in New York City. As President of the Anonymous Arts Recovery Society, he rescued and stored cornices, capitals, portals, columns and other architectural fragments of historical and aesthetic interest from demolition sites. Many are displayed in his Anonymous Arts Museum, Charlotteville, NY and some became part of a sculpture garden that Karp donated to the Brooklyn Museum of Art.
While Leo Castelli Gallery was closed for summer vacations in 1963 and 1964, Karp ran his own contemporary art gallery in Provincetown. He named it OK Harris, a name he thought suggestive of a colorful, very American character. A few years later, Karp opened OK Harris Works of Art in SoHo where a portrait of a bearded man titled "Oscar Klondike Harris" hung in his office. "Mr. Harris" frequently assumed blame for delays, rejections and other unwelcome news or decisions. OK Harris Works of Art (first at 469 West Broadway and later at 383 West Broadway) was a 10,000 square foot ground-floor space where as many as six concurrent solo exhibitions were presented every six weeks. The goal was "to exhibit the broadest spectrum of the most adventuresome art being offered" and the focus was on emerging artists, many of them unknown. In addition to being at the forefront of the Photo-realist movement in 1969, OK Harris Works of Art was the first gallery to exhibit the work of Duane Hanson, Deborah Butterfield, Manny Farber, Richard Pettibone, Robert Cottingham, Robert Bechtle, Marilyn Levine, Nancy Rubins, Malcolm Morley, Luis Jiminez, Jake Berthot, Jack Goldstein, Porfirio DiDonna, and Al Souza.
An approachable, friendly man who enjoyed sharing his knowledge, Karp usually sat at the gallery's front desk and was available to all. Unlike many dealers, he was willing to look at and discuss artists' slides, offered encouragement, and often followed up with studio visits.
At his request, Marilynn Gelfman Karp became gallery director after her husband's death in 2012. She ran the business with gallery staff including Ivan's oldest son, Ethan. Following Ivan's guidelines, OK Harris Works of Art closed with a gala celebration 2014 for all the gallery's artists, collectors and friends.
Baeder, John; Butterfield, Deborah, 1949-; Castanis, Muriel, 1926-; Celender, Don, 1931-2005; Clarke, John Clem, 1937-; De Andrea, John, 1941-; Dufresne, Leonard, 1941-; Goings, Ralph; Grinder, Robert; Hanson, Duane, 1925-1996; Kacere, John C., 1920-1999; Karp, Marilynn Gelfman; McLean, Richard Thorpe, 1934-; Rohm, Robert; Salt, John, 1937-; Wesselmann, Tom, 1931-2004; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Diaries; Photo-realism; Photographs; Prints
- Correspondence, 1960-2013; Series 1; 2.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 92
  Arrangement note
  Additional correspondence is found among the arists' files (Series 4).
  Scope and Contents note
  The personal and professional correspondence of Ivan C. Karp includes letters addressed to Ivan Karp, Marilynn Gelfman Karp, the couple, and to the gallery. Typed letters, e-mail, and handwritten items sometimes show Karp's canny sense of humor. Included are Karp's responses to detailed questions from graduate students and art professionals regarding his areas of expertise, as well as letters of reference or support. Many letters from established members of the art world and others express gratitude to the Karps for their helpfulness and generosity. Correspondents include museums, schools, galleries, dealers, collectors, and artists.
  Some items of note include a letter from Chuck Close asking for Karp's support for a fellow artist with a neurological disorder. Correspondence between Marilynn Gelfman-Pereira Karp and Jasper Johns (signed in his absence by assistant Mark Lancaster) is about stabilizing Savarin Coffee Can with Brushes. An e-mail from President Obama to "Ivan" thanks him for supporting the passage of the Affordable Health Care Act. Letters from Karp to Hilton Kramer and William Grimes express his opinions on issues of the day. More typical, are letters written by Karp concerning gallery business and his opinions about the value or authenticity of specific works.
  Holiday cards received by the Karps are mostly handmade. Also found are letters to art critic Andy Grundberg of The New York Times questioning why he seldom reviews exhibitions at OK Harris Works of Art; many of these letters are blind copies received by Karp.
  - Correspondence, General (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Ivan Karp, 1970-2012; undated; Includes 1 electronic disc (CD) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Letters to The New York Times (Andy Grundberg), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Handmade Holiday Cards, 1990s-2011; undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Holiday Cards, 1988-2005; undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Thanks and Commendations, 1976-2014; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Artist and Collector Friends' Responses to Marilynn Karp's Manuscript, "I Married an Art Dealer", 2014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Artists' Letters to Ivan and Marilynn Karp (Box 1)
    - Abraham, Daryl, 1980; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Algardi, Alessandro, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Arman, undated; 1981-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Baeder, John, undated; 1978-2014 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Bechtle, Robert, undated; 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Berhang, Mattie, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Berthot, Jake, undated; 2011 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bolati, Roland, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bond, Douglas, 1980-1982; undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Butterfield, Deborah, 1979; undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Celender, Don, 1975-1993; undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Clarke, John Clem and Jane P. Clarke, undated; 1978-2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cone, Davis, undated; 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Cottingham, Robert, undated; 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - DeAndrea, John, undated; 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Douke, Dan, undated; 1985-1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Defresne, Leonard, undated; 1984-2013 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Erró, 1976; undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Fawcett, John, circa 1985-2000; undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Furman, David, 1990-1991; undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Ginder, Robert and Cara Wood Ginder, 1990-2014; undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Goings, Ralph and Shannah Goings, undated; 1984-2013 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Hanson, Duane and Wesla (Liz) Hanson, undated; 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Harrison, Alan, 1985-2012 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Johns, Jasper; Mark Lancaster, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Kacere, John and Maja Bankava, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lamagna, Carlo and Kathryn (Kitty Hollenbeck) Lamagna, 1982-2014; undated (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
    - Lazarevich, Milo, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Levine, Marilyn, 1984; undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Lichtenstein, Roy and Dorothy Lichtenstein, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Lippold, Richard, undated; 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - McLean, Richard, 1977-2010; 1977-2012; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Pettibone, Richard and Shirley Pettibone, undated; 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Roggee, Edward, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Rohm, Robert, 1997-2013 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Salt, John and Jean Salt, undated; 1973-2013 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Samaras, Lucas, 1989-2014 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Van Patten, James, 2001-2007 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Van Vranken, Robert, undated; 1989-2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Wesselmann, Tom and Claire Wesselmann, undated; 1974-2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Wines, James, undated; 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Artists' Letters, A-Z (1-2 each), 1960-2014; undated (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - Artists' Letters to Joan Farrell, OK Harris Bookkeeper, 1970s-2003 (Box 92, Folder 15)
  - Collectors, 2011-2014 (Box 92, Folder 16)
  - Condolence Letters (Box 2)
    - To Marilynn Karp, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 17-38)
    - To Marilynn Karp, 2012-2013 (Box 92, Folder 1-5)
    - To OK Harris and Ethan Karp, 2012 (Box 92, Folder 6-8)
    - To Jesse Karp, 2012 (Box 92, Folder 9)
    - Regarding OK Harris Works of Art, 2012 (Box 92, Folder 10)
    - Notes and Donations to Anonymous Arts Recovery Society, sent c/o OK Harris Works of Art and Marilynn Karp, 2012 (Box 92, Folder 11)
    - Internet Condolences and Blogs; e-mail to OK Harris Works of Art and Marilynn Karp, 2012 (Box 92, Folder 12)
  - Museum People, 1976-2014; undated (Box 92, Folder 13)
  - Responses to Annoncement of OK Harris Closing, 2014 (Box 92, Folder 14)
- Administrative Files, 1969-2014; Series 2; 0.7 Linear feet Box 3
  This series documents the manner in which OK Harris Works of Art conducted business. There are forms for reccurring activities, statements of business practices, and materials to guide gallery personnel in dealings with visitors and artists. Other records concern experiments with selling postcards, reproductions, and the OK Now Watch at the gallery. Also found are samples of announcements, invitations, advertising, and a few files on miscellaneous projects that were important to Ivan and Marilynn Karp.
  - Advertising, 1977-2012; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Announcements/Invitations to Group Shows, 1972-2008; undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Artists' Statements, 2002-2012; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Collectibles Exhibitions, 1970-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibitions: California State University at Long Beach, "People/Places, 1948-1963" and Centre College, Danville, Kentucky, 1982-2013 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Schedules, 1969-2014 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Forms, 1996-1998; undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Form Letters, 1984-2012; undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Front Desk Materials, 1986-2010; undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gallery Floor Plans and Signs, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Gallery Statements and List of Artists, undated; 1970-circa 2012 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hallway Exhibitions, 1990-1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hotel and Visitor Information, 1989-2013; undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Limited Edition Prints/Cone Baeder, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Memorabilia/Special Events, 1964-2013; undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Memorabalia/Special Event Business Records, 1983-2014; undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Memorial Book List, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Obituary Information, 1998-2013; undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - OK Harris 20th Anniversary Celebration, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - OK Harris 30th Anniversary Celebration, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - OK Now Watch, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photography Exhibitions, 1971-2010 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Postcards, Catalog and Book List, 1990-1998; undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Press Releases, 1993-2010 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Prints, Retail, 1982-2005; undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Recipients Awarded the OK Harris Medal, 1969-2014 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Reproduction Rights, 1994-2013; undated (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - Statistics for Advertising and Printed Matter, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Visitor Sign-In Pages, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Exhibition Files, 1969-2014; Series 3; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Exhibition files document a small number of group exhibitions, collectibles and antique exhibitions (from private collections), summer invitationals, and special event exhibitions. The files include a wide range of materials in varying combinations, among them: price lists, resumes, installation layouts, press releases, exhibition announcements, brochures, clippings of reviews, photographs and slides of artwork and exhibition installations.
  Files of note include "Ivan's Choices: Icons of Hyper-Realism" (2012 January 6-2013 March 2) and "Ivan C. Karp: People/Places, 1948-1963" (2013 January 6-March 2); both exhibitions were selected and arranged by Karp. Also of interest are records regarding the final show held by OK Harris Works of Art (2014 March 9-April 18) featuring work by many of the gallery's artists.
  Exhibition schedules are followed by exhibition files arranged in categories established by the gallery: group exhibitions, collectibles exhibitions, antique exhibitions, special event exhibitions, and summer invitationals. This series is incomplete. Similar materials concerning solo exhibitions are found in the artists' files (Series 4). Additional exhibition schedules are included with printed material (Series 5). Complete visual documentation of exhibition installations throughuot the gallery's 45 year history is found among the photographic materials (Series 7).
  - Exhibition Schedules, 1969-2011 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - List of Exhibitions at OK Harris, 1970-2008 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Group Show Resumes, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Group Exhibitions - World War I Posters (undated), circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Group Exhibitions - "Arcadia" (2012 June 3-July 20) (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Group Exhibitions - "Ivan's Choices: Icons of Hyper-Realism" (2013 January 6-March 2) and "Ivan C. Karp: People/Places, 1948-1963" (2013 January 6-March 2), Includes 2 electronic discs (CD); 1 electronic disc (DVD). (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Group Exhibitions - Final O.K. Harris Show (2014 March 9-April 18) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Collectibles Exhibitions - "19th Century American Stoneware" (1974 November 9-30) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Collectibles Exhibitions - "Art Deco Sculpture" (1976) (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Antique Exhibitions - "17th-18th Century European Tools" (1980 May 24 - June 14) (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Antique Exhibitions - "Antique Bicycles and Related Phenomena" (1983-1984) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Antique Exhibitions - "Antique Trade Labels" (1986) (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Antique Exhibitions - "Vintage Board Games" (1993 May-July 16) (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Special Event Exhibitions - "Art at the Armory" (1988 January 28-31) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Special Event Exhibitions - "Art against AIDS" (1987) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Special Event Exhibitions - "Vietnamese Propaganda Art" (1995 September 16-October 7) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Special Event Exhibitions - "I Love New York Benefit" (2001 October 17-November 3) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Special Event Exhibitions - "American Abstract Artists, 75th Anniversary Exhibition" (2011 November 3-27) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Summer Invitationals (1975-2007), 1974-2007 (Box 4, Folder 6-13)
  - Summer Invitationals - "Centennial Biennial Invitational" (1991 June 1-July 12) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Summer Invitationals - "The Big Picture" (1992 May 30-July 17) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Summer Invitationals - "Subject: Object" (2003 May 31-July 18 and 2003 September 2-September 6) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Summer Invitationals - "Illuminators" (2013 June 1-July 19 and 2013 September 3-September 7) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Letters from Artists Seeking an Exhibition at OK Harris" (circa 2008-circa 2012), circa 1980-circa 2012 (Box 4, Folder 18-21)
- Artists' Files, 1967-2014; Series 4; 34 Linear feet Boxes 4-38, 80
  Artists' files consist of business and personal correspondence, biographical information, checklists, contracts, receipts, printed material, photographs, slides and color transparencies in various combinations. The files document arrangements for exhibitions, loans, consignments, shipping, and miscellaneous transactions with OK Harris Works of Art. The most extensively documented artists are: John Baeder, Muriel Castanis, Don Celender, Ralph Goings, John Kacere, Richard McLean, Robert Rohm and John Salt. Files regarding Don Celender include many of his surveys that were exhibited at OK Harris. Ephemera from Celender exhibitions consists of three different boxes for "OK Harris Art Crackers" based on the traditional animal cracker box, and two Chinese take out cartons of "Art Dealers Fortune Cookies" and "Art Curators Fortune Cookies."